Can you move out
of the way, though?
You gotta move over here, sir.
OK, thank you.
Hey.
How you guys doing, huh?
Today we're going to be
introducing our two new muntjac,
Tyler and Peanut, to Chowlie.
Muntjac are a small
Asian species.
What I like about them is,
they like to hide,
and they're very, very sneaky.
They actually were introduced
also, in England, and they're
kind of a nuisance in England.
I just find it very interesting
that an animal from Asia was
introduced into an area where
they're not supposed to be.
They're also called
barking deer.
That's how they communicate
with each other and warn each
other of any kind of danger,
which I think is kind of cool.
Here you go, Chowlie girl.
Chowlie, she's going to be kind
of like the grandma
of the bunch.
She's an older female, but she
's experienced out there.
So I see her really kind
of taking the leadership role.
There's such a cute animal.
Everybody thinks they're
babies, they are not.
Tyler and Peanut are still doing
a little bit of growing,
but for the most part, they
are a very small deer species.
They're a year
and two years old.
And they're just really fun.
Everyone loves Chowlie,
so these two are just going
to be a great
addition to our area.
This is our little makeshift
wall that we use a lot of times,
when we're doing introductions
with hoofstock.
And it's solid,
so the deer can see it.
The tough thing about muntjac,
is they get wound
up really easy.
I mean, they can
overheat really quickly.
It's actually pretty
frustrating, because sometimes
you're like, just calm down,
it's not that big a deal.
And it's really a small
hoofstock, a small
ungulate thing.
These guys are food,
so if there is aggression,
and we get some chasing
and stuff like that,
we can quickly try to time
that and separate them,
and stop that aggression
if that happens.
Let's get two more sheets.
Hi, cute deer.
So I've been at the zoo
about 24 years.
And one of the things I love is,
I really look at what
animals behaviors are.
Excuse me.
Can we talk some more?
I try very hard not to analyze
them and put my own impressions
on them, but it's
kind of hard not to.
Hey.
We've been talking
all night long.
This is my formal
greeting, I am Tyler.
It's just-- it geeks me out.
Easy.
I got it.
You're all right.
I think, yeah.
I think they'll be
excited to be outside.
All right, good luck.
OK, ready?
We
open the crates,
and as soon as we get them open,
they, of course, jump out
and go pretty quickly.
They think they kind of realize,
oh, we're outside, you know.
So then I think it kind of calms
down once they're
out of the crate.
I like this tree,
it's very delicious.
Quick, look at all these grass.
Where is Chowlie?
Hope she gets up investigates.
Oh, there she is, OK.
Chowlie's still laying down,
not caring about anything.
Chowlie is just laying down
right now, so she hasn
't really gotten up.
I'm sure she notices something's
going on, because obviously,
us coming in with crates
is not her norm.
But right now, she's calm,
she's laying down,
while they're kind
of investigating their area.
So you have some friends.
Yeah.
I think everything went well.
Hopefully those two will
interact through the lattice,
and we'll see what they do,
and we'll continue tomorrow.