The nest building is like
a miracle of nature,
in my opinion.
(water rushing softly)
I didn't know that Zoom could
curl up her tail like that.
Her grip needs to be strong
to hold onto that vegetation.
To see Zoom come out
of the water with her full load
of nesting materials
and then disappear into a tiny
burrow, it's incredible.
How does all that stuff
even fit in the burrow?
The platypus can hardly
fit through that hole.
She's constructing that nest
in 100% darkness.
We were super fortunate
to find Zoom's burrow.
So my strategy is to place
a number of trail cameras around
that burrow, out of her way,
and just leave them running.
When they see something happen,
they'll send me an alert.
When I woke up one morning
and looked at my phone I saw two
or three alerts from the trail
cameras around
that nesting burrow.
It was like,
something's gone down.
Easy.
All right, the moment of truth.
To
see a youngster come out of Zoom
's burrow was such
a magical feeling.
(laughing)
And the next day I'd come down
to the pond here and I've just
been walking around for a few
minutes looking for him.
There's me walking around
looking for him everywhere,
but the whole time
he'd been behind me.
(light music)
(water rushing softly)
Young platypus are so vulnerable
and so clumsy.
(water splashing)
But Zoom's work as
a mother is done.
Now her baby's out
of the burrow, he'll have to
find his own way in the world.
(birds chittering)
Zoom's youngster gives me hope
that platypus can continue
living in this city.
(light music fades out)