Plastic. 12 million tons of it
end up in the ocean every year.
Each year, it's likely over half
a million animals are ensnared
and killed by these ghost nets.
But some animals are learning
how to take advantage of the
plastic rafts... and use them
for shelter or even as a home.
This male Columbus crab, barely
bigger than your thumbnail, is a
castaway. Clinging to his net,
he may have been drifting on
ocean currents for months. Now
fully grown, he needs to find a
partner. Columbus crabs are not
good swimmers. So this male is
marooned.
Perhaps a passing loggerhead
turtle could be the chance to
hitch a lift.
Made it. But there is more than
one passenger here -- a female
Columbus Crab.
They waste no time
in getting aquainted.
And start to mate.
This pair may well stay together
for the rest of their lives.
The turtle, after all, makes an
excellent home. In return, the
crabs provide an onboard
grooming service.