The barn owl is unquestionably a
beautiful bird. It has a
distinctive heart-shaped face,
mottled brown and grey wings
with pure white underparts. They
have a wingspan of around 80-95
cm and weigh in at 250-350g. It
is considered to be one of
Britain's most popular birds and
one of the more commonly seen
owls due to its readiness to
hunt during the day, although
dusk is probably the best time
to see one. They are silent
hunters, tiny serrations on the
leading edges of their flight
feathers and a hairlike fringe
on the trailing edges help to
break up the flow of air over
the wings and this reduces
turbulence and the noise it
would cause. The barn owl flies
slowly while hunting and will
hover over spots where prey
might be hiding. The barn owl
has fantastic hearing with
asymmetrical ears which improves
the owl's ability to pinpoint
the position and distance of
sounds. Their heart-shaped face
also aids the owl's ability to
hear. It's been shown that if
the ruff feathers are removed,
the owl can still determine the
sounds position, but not its
height. Barn owls' main source
of prey are rodents and other
small mammals, in fact, over 90%
of an owl's diet is made up of
such animals. But it will also
prey upon other birds, lizards,
amphibians, fish, spiders, and
insects. The barn owl has a high
metabolic rate, more so than
most other owls of a similar
size. This means it requires
relatively more food.
Observations have shown that the
barn owl will eat around 14% of
its own body weight of rodents
per night. It may also store
excess food at roosting sites
which it will return to if food
is scarce. Their high rate of
rodent kills makes them very
valuable to farmers who wish to
keep the rodent population down.
Barn owls are said to be more
effective than poison for rodent
control. As their name suggests,
barn owls will nest in cavities
of barns and old buildings as
well as hollows of trees. Nests
are built on top of the previous
year's nests. There is no set
breeding season for these owls,
and this largely depends on the
available food supply, but most
commonly occurs between March
and August. Around 4-6 eggs will
be laid and up to 2 broods will
be raised in a year. Barn owls
are fairly common and be seen
all over Britain and Ireland,
although populations are under
threat in Northern Ireland. They
did go through a dramatic
population decline all over
Britain during the 1950s and
60s, dipping down to as low as
4000 breeding pairs. This was
most likely due to the use of
toxic farm chemicals such as
DDT, but also loss of hunting
habitat, and two particularly
harsh winters of 1946/47 and
1962/63. Barn owls can also be
susceptible to poisoning by
ingesting rodents killed by
rodenticides. Nesting sites are
also scarce due to many old
barns and buildings being
demolished or renovated.
Luckily, population numbers are
thought to be on the rise due to
improved conservation efforts
and many nest boxes being built.
These nest boxes have also
allowed populations of owls to
inhabit areas that they
previously were absent from,
such as the fens. Although it
seems the population is fairly
healthy, having increased to
around 14,000 breeding pairs, it
is acknowledged that monitoring
of nocturnal birds is difficult
and population studies are
somewhat unreliable. Barn owls
have a typical lifespan of
around 4 years, typically
breeding at 1 year. However, the
oldest confirmed age by the
British Trust for Ornithology,
was 15 years, 3 months, and 21
days.