The barn owl is unquestionably
a beautiful bird.
It has
a distinctive heart-shaped face,
mottled brown and grey wings
with pure white underparts.
They have a wingspan
of around 80-95 cm and weigh in
at 250-350g.
It is considered to be one
of Britain's most popular birds
and one of the more
commonly seen owls
due to its readiness to hunt
during the day,
although dusk is probably
the best time to see one.
They are silent hunters,
tiny serrations
on the leading edges of their
flight feathers
and a hairlike fringe
on the trailing edges
help to break up the flow of air
over the wings and this reduces
turbulence and the noise
it would cause.
The barn owl flies slowly
while hunting and will hover
over spots where prey
might be hiding.
The barn owl has
fantastic hearing
with asymmetrical ears
which improves the owl's ability
to pinpoint the position
and distance of sounds.
Their heart-shaped face
also aids the owl's ability
to hear.
It's been shown
that if the ruff feathers
are removed,
the owl can still determine
the sounds position,
but not its height.
Barn owls' main source of prey
are rodents
and other small mammals,
in fact,
over 90% of an owl's diet
is made up of such animals.
But it will also prey
upon other birds, lizards,
amphibians, fish, spiders,
and insects.
The barn owl has
a high metabolic rate,
more so than most other owls
of a similar size.
This means it requires
relatively more food.
Observations have shown
that the barn owl will eat
around 14% of its own body
weight of rodents per night.
It may also store excess food
at roosting sites which it
will return to if food is
scarce.
Their high rate of rodent kills
makes them very valuable
to farmers who
wish to keep the rodent
population down.
Barn owls
are said to be more effective
than poison for rodent control.
As their name suggests,
barn owls will nest
in cavities of barns
and old buildings as well
as hollows of trees.
Nests are built on top
of the previous year's nests.
There is no set breeding season
for these owls,
and this largely depends
on the available food supply,
but most commonly occurs
between March and August.
Around 4-6 eggs will be laid
and up to 2 broods
will be raised in a year.
Barn owls are fairly common
and be seen all over Britain
and Ireland,
although populations are
under threat in Northern
Ireland.
They did
go through a dramatic population
decline all over Britain
during the 1950s and 60s,
dipping down to as low as 4000
breeding pairs.
This was most likely
due to the use of toxic farm
chemicals such as DDT,
but also
loss of hunting habitat,
and two
particularly harsh winters
of 1946/47 and 1962/63.
Barn owls can also be
susceptible to poisoning
by ingesting rodents killed
by rodenticides.
Nesting sites are also scarce
due to many old barns
and buildings being demolished
or renovated.
Luckily,
population numbers
are thought to be on the rise
due to improved conservation
efforts and many nest boxes
being built.
These nest boxes have
also allowed populations of owls
to inhabit areas that they
previously were absent from,
such as the fens.
Although it seems the population
is fairly healthy,
having increased
to around 14,000 breeding pairs,
it is acknowledged
that monitoring
of nocturnal birds is difficult
and population studies are
somewhat unreliable.
Barn owls have
a typical lifespan of around 4
years,
typically breeding at 1 year.
However,
the oldest confirmed age
by the British Trust
for Ornithology, was 15 years,
3 months, and 21 days.
The barn owl is clearly
a beautiful bird,
easy on the eyes you might say,
but not so easy on the ears.
Other names for this bird
include 'screech owl,
and 'demon owl'
which might give you some idea
as to what they sound like!
But this is the'
beautiful birds' series,
not' beautiful sounding birds'
series,
so its place is well deserved.
Thank you
for watching this month's video,
I hope you enjoyed that one.
Please do leave a like if you
did,
and make sure
you subscribe for more videos
like this one.
I hope to see you back here
for the next video, until then,
have a great day and I'll see
you soon.
Goodbye.